## Heath O'Brien, PhD

#### Bioinformatician

November 2019

• 10 Marmaduke Street, Bristol BS3 4SQ, United Kingdom

+44 (0) 7711 045747

hobrien.github.io

heath.obrien@gmail.com

**y** heath obrien

nobrien

hdQp2NsAAAJ

heath-o-brien-198145b2

### About me —

I have 20 years of experience analyzing genetic data, both in academia and the private sector. I've worked on functional genomics, high-throughput sequencing and genotyping data from plants, fungi, bacteria and humans. I enjoy working on interdisciplinary projects and leading teams with diverse skill sets. I also have strong communication skills, having co-authored over 25 publications and presented my research at conferences in 7 countries.

# Skills —

Functional genomics

Quantitative genetics

Microbiology

Data visualisation

Scientific communication

Project management

R

Python

BASH

AWS

 $\operatorname{SQL}$ 

Work History

2018-Present Lead Bioinformatician

Living DNA

- Leading a team of 6 bioinformaticians and data scientists developing methods to derive ancestry and health insights from direct-to-consumer genetics
- Managing partnerships with data suppliers, academic scientists and business incubators
- Working to secure external funding to develop novel genomic prediction approaches
- Collaboration with the engineering team to deploy processing pipelines at scale and to improve all steps of sample processing and data delivery

2016-2018 Research Associate

Cardiff, UK

Frome, UK

MRC Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics

- Differential gene expression and eQTL analyses on human brain samples
- Integration of functional genomics data with largescale population genomics datasets for schizophrenia and other neurophychiatric disorders
- Organization of training seminars on data science (Rstudio, MySQL), version control (Git), and pipeline development (Snakemake, Bash)
- Deployment of results on the web using R-Shiny

2013-2016 Bioinformatician

Bristol, UK

- University of Bristol
  Comparative transcriptomics to determine the genetic basis of cell wall patterning responsible for colour-production in plant leaves
  - Electron microscopy of light scattering nanostructures in plants and algae
  - Acting group leader during nine-month family leave cover (overseeing a team of three staff and two students, managing procurement)

2008-2013 Postdoctoral Fellow

Toronto, ON, Canada

University of Toronto

- De novo assembly and comparative analyses of bacterial genomes
- Cloning of virulence factors and characterization using in-planta infection assays
- Supervision of undergraduate students

2006-2008 Lab Administrator

Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

- Oversight of teaching labs for General and Advanced Microbiology
- Managed one lab technician and eight teaching assistants

### Education

2000-2006 PhD, Molecular systematics of cyanobacteria Durham, NC, USA

Duke University

1994-1999 Bachelors degree, Plant Science Edmonton, AB, Canada

University of Alberta

### Training

 ${\bf Advanced\ Python\ for\ Biologists,\ PR\ Statistics,\ February,\ 2017}.$ 

Advancing in R, PR Statistics, April, 2015.

Genetic Data Analysis, Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics, June, 2003.

#### [References]

Available on request.